Guide to the George M. Fredrickson Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
George M. Fredrickson papers
1965-2002
1980-2002
SC0706
Fredrickson, George M., 1934-2008
18.25 Linear feet
Papers largely reflect his career as historian and professor and include course files, conference and organizational files, lectures, articles and papers, and correspondence. Most of the course files are from those he taught at Stanford University, with a few from courses at Northwestern. Subjects include Civil War, race relations, and African American history.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
George M. Fredrickson, the Edgar E. Robinson Professor of United States History (emeritus) at Stanford University, earned his A.B. (1956) and Ph.D. (1964) from Harvard; he matriculated as a Fulbright Scholar at the University of Oslo (1956-7) and was awarded an honorary M.A. from Oxford University in 1988. He taught at Harvard and Northwestern before joining the history faculty at Stanford in 1984. He has published seven books on the Civil War, African American history, and racism and published numerous articles, including more than twenty-five pieces in THE NEW YORK REVIEW OF BOOKS. In 1985, he was elected a fellow of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences. He was also a co-director of the Research Institute of Comparative Studies in Race and Ethnicity at Stanford and in 2000 was awarded the Cox Medal for fostering undergraduate research.
Description of the Collection
Papers largely reflect his career as historian and professor and include course files, conference and organizational files, lectures, articles and papers, and correspondence. Most of the course files are from those he taught at Stanford University, with a few from courses at Northwestern. Subjects include Civil War, race relations, and African American history.
Access Terms
Fredrickson, George M., 1934-2008; Stanford University. Department of History.; African Americans --History --Study and teaching (Higher).; United States--History--Study and teaching (Higher).
Collection Contents
- Papers, Accession ARCH-2004-132
  - Publications: White Supremacy and related files
    - Promotion (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Responses to (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Reviews (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - New York Review piece on ANC (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 8th grade text (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Review of Inner Civil War (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Republication of Inner Civil War (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Black Image: Reviews, Correspondence, etc. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Black Image: Reprint (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Responses to Arrogance of Race manuscript (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Historiography of Post-Emancipation Race Relations (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Review of Woodward for Dissent (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - New York Review article on S. A. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Book Reviews before ‘73 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Burgess Project (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Jr. Brittanica article on Racism (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Publication of South Africa Study (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Black Liberation book (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Veblen Essay (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Hedda Gabbler Essay (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - BP/BC in Sout Africa Essay (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Northwestern courses:
    - Bio American Mission (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - History B10-1 (US as a Plural Society) (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - History B10 lectures 1980 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Stanford courses and general files:
    - History 164 Lectures (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - 19th century Lectures (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - CSRE (Comparative Studies in Race and Ethnicity) (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - History 164 Old lectures (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - 165B lectures (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - History 159A lectures (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Moscow State University Reconstruction Era (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - 159B lectures (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - [Comparative History Essay—Seminar] (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - [Book of Essays] (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - [Book of Essays—unused material] (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - [Racism paper final draft] (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - [Northwestern C06-1 The South in American History] (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Lectures on Historiography of Slaves and the Old South (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - [New York Review piece on South Africa] (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Lectures at other universities (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Oxford lectures Civil War and Reconstruction (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Comparative History (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Copies of Unpublished Papers (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Mary Lincoln talk (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Review of David Montgomery The Fall of the House of Labor (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Comparative History Collection (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Reconstruction lecture (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Comparative history series (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Elite in the Civil War Crisis draft (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Lectures in Britain and Europe (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Comparative lecture (US and South Africa) (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Lectures on 19th century historiography (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Comparative history paper (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - CETECS (course file) (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Frankfurt Conference (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Gilded Age Lectures (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Northwestern University C-14 lectures (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Arrogance of Race book (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Moscow course (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Reviews of White Supremacy (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Imperialism and the Intellectuals possible paper (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - German lectures (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - 1865-1900 project (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Black Image lecture (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - University of Chicago lecture (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Lecture based on White Supremacy (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - UNESCO Courier article (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Book: Salmagundi: Afro-American at the Start of a New Century (Box 3)
    - Salmagundi correspondence (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Review of book on Du Bois (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - New York Review pieces on racism (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Marx and Massie Review (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - New Republic review of Seigal (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Non-violence paper (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Thornstrom Review (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Reviews miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Osolfsky lecture (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - ANB Helper (American National Biography) (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Library of America (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - South 30s 40s Review NYRB (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Review of Kolchin/Bowman (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Religion and Civil War conference (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Thomas Festsprach (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - JAH essay Comparative History (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Michigan State conference (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - London seminar (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Colorado lecture (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - New York Times Review—Blacks and Jews (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - NYRB John Hope Franklin book (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Review of Lynching book (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - USIA handbook (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - UNESCO article original draft (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Leipzig conference (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Coe history workshop (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Naples conference (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Fulbright lectureship Italy (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Dissent multiculturalism article (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Jasper, Texas (relates to Lynching folder) (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Evans intro (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - OAH Otterbein lectures (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Bridging Cultural Divides (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence 1988-1997 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - R & E Institute planning (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Sonoma conference (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Irvine conference (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence 1994-1996 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - CIV essential documents (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Course file 351B 1994 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Course file 164 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Course file 351B (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Course file 164 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Course file 164 syllabi etc. (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - More CIV (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Miscellaneous lectures (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Gettysburg lecture (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Shaw monument (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - San Marino conference (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - AHA 2002 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - SHA 1996 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - OHA Los Angeles (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - AHA 1999 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Turner Prize committee (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - OAH 1994 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - OAH 1996 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - AHA 1984 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - OHA presidency (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Presidential addresses (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Presidential addresses (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - AHA 1976 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Duke conference 1977 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Upsalla conference 1977-1978 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - OAH 1986 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - SHA 1995 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - SSHA meeting 1996 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - OAH 2002 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Guadalupe conference (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Michigan State conference (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - IESBS Article on Hist. Racism (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Du Bois revised (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Comparative Imagination (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Tocqueville translation (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - New York Times Review of Books review of book by Ira Berlin (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Rome conference (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - German Historical Institute Washington DC conference (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - New York Review piece on Malcolm X and Sobukwe (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Charleston lecture (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Utah State OAH lecture (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - History 164 1991 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Santa Barbara conference (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - American Anthropological Association Santa Barbara (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - South Africa trip SEF project (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Trip to Africa, visas etc. (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - History 271A 1989 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - History 271 Fall 1990 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - History 351C 1986-1987 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Southeast Mass. visit (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Curt Prize (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Craven Committee (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - History 159B 1986-1987 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - History 454 1987 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - History 454 Spring 1990 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Huntington lecture (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Travel notes and expenses, Summer 1965 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Madison lecture (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - SHA program 1986 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - AHA paper 1985 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - History 454 1985-1986 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence 1985-1986 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - OAH executive secretary review committee (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - History 159 1984 (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - AHA candidacy (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - International Congress of Historical Societies (Madrid) 1989-1990 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Teach-In Rodney King 1992 (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - Afro-Am Intellectual History Harvard (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - German trip lectures (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - Florida trip 1985 (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - Yale seminar 1985 (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - History 259A 1985 (Box 6, Folder 36)
    - Slotkin Review (Box 6, Folder 37)
    - SUNY Binghamton lectureship 1987 (Box 6, Folder 38)
    - Cal Poly lecture 1987 (Box 6, Folder 38)
    - Cal Longbeach lecture 1987 (Box 6, Folder 39)
    - History 271 1987 (Box 6, Folder 40)
    - History 271A 1984-85 (Box 6, Folder 41)
    - History 351C (Box 6, Folder 42)
    - History 351C 1990 (Box 6, Folder 43)
    - OAH session 1984 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Cornell comp history series (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Amer Academy of arts and sciences (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - NEH fellowship & Rockefeller fellowship 1985/86 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Misc correspondence 1984-85 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Misc correspondence 1983-84 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - DuBois institute (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Newcastle conference 1994 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - OAH business (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Soviet writings on U. S. history (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Ethnic Studies course, SU (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Hutchison papers (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Hist 454 1991 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Colloquium 351C 1991-92 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Hist 341D 1994 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - SHA session (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - East Carolina conference 1986 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - VASO hosting Russian scholar (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Mississippi symposium 1990 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Paris lectures race relations 1987-88 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - OAH session 1987 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - SHA convention 1989 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Cal-Poly address 1991 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Hist 271A Spring 1987 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Plagiarism case Sokolow case [needs folder] (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - Hist 159B Fall 87 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - Teaching at Tours 1988 (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Hist 351C 1988 (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - Ohio Univ lecture 1988 (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - Misc publications (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - Personal correspondence (Box 7, Folder 31)
    - Possible South Africa lecture 1983/84 (Box 7, Folder 32)
    - South Africa visit 1988 (Box 7, Folder 33)
    - MTR film 1985 (Box 7, Folder 34)
    - Rochon case (Box 7, Folder 35)
    - Coe seminar (Box 7, Folder 36)
    - OAH board meeting April 1986 (Box 7, Folder 37)
    - Williamson essay NYRB (Box 7, Folder 38)
    - Georgia conference 1987/88 (Box 7, Folder 39)
    - Paris conference 1991 (Box 7, Folder 40)
    - NY review essay Post-CW South (Box 7, Folder 41)
    - Howard lecture 1988 (Box 7, Folder 42)
    - Past lectures misc (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Toronto lectures 1984 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - NYRB article on F. Douglas (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Amer Academy of Arts and Sciences fellows 1985 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - 18th Century conference session 1985 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - New Republic South Africa review (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - North Carolina visit, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Pulitzer Prize 1983 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Dunning & Beveredge Prizes (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Fullbright to Moscow, practical matters, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Phi Beta Kappa prize 1981 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Intellectual history methodology (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Admissions committee (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - American ? (faculty search file) (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - African American search file 1996 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Reviews 1977-84 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence re early publications (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Visiting lectureship at Rice 1984 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - C17 Northwestern course (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Personal correspondence 1960s (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Beveredge & Dunning prize 1982 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - South African projects (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Comments on papers (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - Northwestern courses reading lists and exams (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - Bibliography project (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - Georgia visit program review 1984 (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - Comparative history conference 1984 (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - Purdue speech 1980 (Box 8, Folder 28)
    - Reviews 1973-77 (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - Comparative Imagination – correspondence file (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - OAH program 1992 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Rawley prize 1992 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Northwestern comparative history conference 1986 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Misc correspondence 1986-87 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - AHA PCB session (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - NY Review piece on rural history (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Hist 454, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Kansas City lecture 1992 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - MIT lecture 1991 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - NYRB Ayers review (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - U of London lecture 1988 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - OAH session 1994 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Times Literary Supplement, review of King book (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - NEH panel 1987 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Western Illinois U (Macomb) lecture 1990 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Emerson Prize, Phi Beta Kappa (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Princeton lecture 1991 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Projected book ideas in black and white (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Ohio Wesleyan lecture 1991 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - ANB editorial committee (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence on film projects (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - Fellowships for students 87-88 (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - Fellowship 1993 (Box 9, Folder 23)
    - Child-saving in the age of professionalism (Box 9, Folder 24)
    - Referring articles and manuscripts (Box 9, Folder 25)
    - TLS review (Box 9, Folder 26)
    - Personal and miscellaneous (Box 9, Folder 27)
    - Hist 351B 1995-96 (Box 9, Folder 28)
    - Hist 351B 1996 (Box 9, Folder 29)
    - Hist 351C 1999 (Box 9, Folder 30)
    - Hist 454 1995 (Box 9, Folder 31)
    - Hist 164 1997 (Box 9, Folder 32)
    - Hist 105B 1997 (Box 9, Folder 33)
    - Hist 164 1999 (Box 9, Folder 34)
    - Hist 164 1998 (Box 9, Folder 35)
    - Hist 259 1995 (Box 9, Folder 36)
    - Hist Lincoln (Box 9, Folder 37)
    - History Lincoln 1998/99 (Box 9, Folder 38)
    - Hist 351C 1998 (Box 9, Folder 39)
    - Hist 165B Winter 1995/96 (Box 9, Folder 40)
    - Hist 351C 2001 (Box 9, Folder 41)
    - Hist 454 1999 (Box 9, Folder 42)
    - Hist 454 1997 (Box 9, Folder 43)
    - Hist 164 Fall 1995 (Box 9, Folder 44)
    - Course evaluations (Box 9, Folder 45)
  - Restricted Files:
    - Tenure case of Karen Sawislak (Box 10)
- Papers, Accession ARCH-2008-103
  - Correspondence, papers by Fredrickson and others, articles, notes, clippings and other materials, 1982-2008 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, papers by Fredrickson and others, articles, notes, clippings and other materials, 1982-2008 (Box 2)
- Additional Material, Accession ARCH-2014-098
  - Between Two Worlds: Reflections of Immigrant Acculturation in Norwegian-American Writing. Honors Essay, Harvard College., 1956 Mar 1 (Box 1)